Guide to the Burnet Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Burnet family papers
1725-1936
MS 114
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
(1 box, 1 folio)
These papers pertain to the interrelated Burnet, West, and Williams families descended from Gilbert Burnet, Bishop of Salisbury, England. Among the papers are the personal correspondence of Richard West (1716-1742), poet; of his sister, Mary West Williams (1715-1800); of her son, the Rev. John Henry Williams (b. 1747); and of her father, Richard West, Sr. (d. 1726), lawyer, playwright and statesman; family genealogies; legal papers; and other material. Included are two letters from doctors discussing various physical ailments in the light of medical knowledge of the time; letters (1724-1726) to Richard West, Sr. (when he was Chancellor of Ireland) from several Government officials, including Granville, Newcastle, and Walpole discussing various affairs of state; a collection of poetry written by Richard West, Jr., and Daniel Gaches; and information on the Dutch estate of Bishop Gilbert Burnet (1643-1715), and especially on the claims of the Rev. John Henry Burnet to the inheritance of that estate.
Burnet family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Henry C. Smith, 1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Richard West (d. 1726), birth year unknown, was a lawyer and a playwright. He married Elizabeth Burnet in April 1714. They had a son, Richard (1716-1742) and a daughter Molly. West died on December 3 1726. (From the Dictionary of National Biography, Vol 20, pages 1249-1250)
Richard West (1716-1742) was born in 1716. He attended Eton and Oxford and died at a young age on June 1, 1742. (From the Dictionary of National Biography, Vol XX, pages 1250-1251.)
A Burnet-West-Williams Family Genealogy is available in the repository.
Scope and Contents
These papers pertain to members of the interrelated Burnet, West, and Williams families descended from Gilbert Burnet, Bishop of Salisbury, England, 1643-1715. The papers have been divided into three groups: the papers of Richard West, d. 1726; the papers of his son, Richard West, 1716-1742; and papers of the Burnet family. Within each group correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author.
The papers of Richard West (d. 1726) consist largely of letters received during the last two years of his life, while he was Chancellor of Ireland. There are letters from government officials concerning affairs of state, including William Wood's patent on copper coinage for Ireland, discontent in Ireland in 1725-1726, and rebellion in Scotland in 1725. Among the correspondents are Richard, Baron Edgecumbe, the receiver-general, vice-treasurer, treasurer of war, and paymaster-general of revenues in Ireland; the Duke of Newcastle, Thomas Pelham-Holles, one of the lords justices, secretary of state for the southern department, and joint secretary of state for Scotland; William Pulteney, Earl of Bath, an active parliamentarian; George Bubb Dodington, Baron of Melcombe, a lord of the treasury and clerk of the pells in Ireland; and Sir Robert Walpole. There is also a letter from West to George I requesting a pension for his family after his death, a copy of the warrant signed by George I granting the pension, and a list of West's estate.
The papers of the younger Richard West consist of three letters and of poems written by West and Daniel Gaches. The poems cover various subjects and are undated except for one "upon the Peace of 1762" written by Gaches, who was then a fellow of Kings College, Cambridge, and censor of the University. Of the three letters, one discusses the state of West's health and another, written by John Williams to West's mother, discusses his education.
The papers of the Burnet family, consisting of correspondence, genealogical papers, and wills, deal almost entirely with the Dutch estate which Bishop Burnet inherited from his wife, Mary Scott, and with the claims of John Henry Williams, great-grandson of Bishop Burnet, to that estate. Exceptions include a letter from Rudyard Kipling to S.M. Acklonby concerning a literary reference, and a letter from William Oliver (1659-1716) about medicines and physical ailments.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three groups: the papers of Richard West, d. 1726; the papers of his son, Richard West, 1716-1742; and papers of the Burnet family.
Families; Medicine -- Early works to 1800; Great Britain -- History -- 18th century; Wills; Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715; Carteret, John, Earl Granville, 1690-1763; Cork, Richard Boyle, 4th Earl of, 1695-1753; Dodington, George Bubb, Baron of Melcombe Regis, 1691-1762; West, Richard, 1716-1742; West, Richard, -1726; Williams, John Henry, 1746 or 1747-1829; Williams, Mary West, 1715-1800; Burnett family; West family; Williams family
- Papers of Richard West (d. 1726)
  - Correspondence
    - Bowes, John (1690-1767), 1726 August 13, 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Burlington, Richard Boyle, 3rd earl of (1695-1753), 1726 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carteret, John, earl Granville (1690- 1763), 1726 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clutterbuck, Thomas, 1726 April-November (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Delafaye, [Thomas?], 1725 August-1726 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Denton, Alex, 1726 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dodington, George Bubb, baron of Melcombe (1691-1762), 1725 Oct, 1726 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Edgecumbe, Richard Edgecumbe, 1st baron (1680-1758), 1725 May-1726 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - George I, king of Great Britain (1660- 1727) (copy), 1726 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Grafton, Charles Fitzroy, 2nd duke of (1683-1757), 1725 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - King, Peter King, 1st baron (1669-1734), 1725 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Newcastle, Thomas Pelham-Holles, 1st duke of (1693-1768), 1725 August-1726 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pococke, [J?], 1726 September-October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pratt, John, 1726 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pulteney, William, earl of Bath (1684-1764), 1725 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Read, Joseph, 1725 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Tuder, Joseph, 1725 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Walpole, Robert, 1st earl of Orford (1676-1745), 1725 November-1726 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - R.W. to George I, king of Great Britain (copy), 1726 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Estate papers, 1727 April 1, 1803 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Papers of Richard West (1716-1742)
  - Correspondence
    - Hollings, Dr. John (d. 1739 ), to R.W. (1716-1742), 1738 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - West, Richard (1716-1742), to ___ Mitchell, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Williams, John (d. 1763), to Elizabeth (Burnet) West, 1739 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Poetry of R.W. and Daniel Gaches, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Burnet family papers
  - Correspondence
    - Acklonby, C.R., to "My dear Aunt", 1936 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brown, Thomas, to John Henry Williams, 1808 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Burgess, Mary (Glover), to Mary (West) Williams, 1780 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Burnet, Thomas (1694-1753), to Mary (West) Williams, 1748-1752 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Burnet, Thomas (d. 1792)
      - ALS to Mary (West) Williams, 1786 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to Dr. Lauret & fils (copy), 1791 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Glover, R., to Mary (West) Williams, 1779 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Guitard, A.T., to N. Horn, 1803 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hunt, Thomas (1696-1774), to John Williams (d. 1763), 1754 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kipling, Rudyard (1865-1936), to S.M. Acklonby, 1896 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Oliver, William (1659-1716), to John Williams (d. 1763), 1703 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Viney, M., to John Henry Williams, 1774 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Williams, John Henry
      - ALS to N. Horn, 1802 August-1803 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - ALS to Mr. Visser, 1802 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - ALS to Dr. Sewell, 1803 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - ALS to unidentified, 1803 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Williams, Mary (West), to John Henry Williams, 1774 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Genealogical papers, 1802, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wills, 1716, 1768 (Box 2)